<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>insert title</title>
            <author>insert author</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>insert name of person or entity that is making the work available</authority>
            <publisher>insert publisher</publisher>
            <distributor>
               <name>insert name of distributor</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>insert address details</addrLine>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <date>insert date when TEI was made available</date>
            <availability>
               <p>insert details about access or license</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>insert description about the source used for this encoding</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p>insert details about editorial principles used in the transcription or encoding of the
            text</p>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fr">French</language>
            <language ident="">insert other languages found in the text</language>
         </langUsage>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person><!--insert personogaphy here--></person>
            </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>insert details related to revisions of text, such as date, editor name,
            etc.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
         
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>insert title part</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <lb/>
            <byline> BY<lb/>
               <docAuthor>insert author name</docAuthor>
            </byline>
            <lb/>
            <epigraph>
               <cit>
                  <quote>insert quotation</quote>
                  <bibl>insert poet attributed to quote</bibl>
               </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Houghton Mifflin insignia</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>BOSTON AND NEW YORK</pubPlace>
               <lb/>
               <publisher>HOUGHTON MIFFLIN COMPANY</publisher>
               <lb/>
               <publisher>The Riverside Press Cambridge</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
               <lb/>
               <docDate when="1913">1913</docDate>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <titlePage>
            <docImprint>COPYRIGHT, <date when="1913">1913</date>, BY WILLA SIBERT CATHER<lb/> ALL
               RIGHTS RESERVED<lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Published <date when="1913-06">June 1913</date>
               </hi>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <div1 type="illustration">
            <ab>
               <hi>ALEXANDRA</hi>
            </ab>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="dedication">
            <ab>
               <hi>TO THE MEMORY OF</hi>
               <lb/>SARAH ORNE JEWETT<lb/>
               <hi>IN WHOSE BEAUTIFUL AND DELICATE WORK<lb/> THERE IS THE PERFECTION<lb/>THAT
                  ENDURES</hi>
            </ab>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="epigraph">
            <lg type="poem">
               <head type="main" rend="center">PRAIRIE SPRING</head>
               <l>insert lines of poem</l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="contents">
            <head type="main">CONTENTS</head>
            <list>
               <item n="1">PART I. THE WILD LAND ..... I</item>
               <item n="2">add additional parts</item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div1 type="part" n="1" xml:id="pt1">
            <head type="main" rend="center">PART I</head>
            <head type="main" rend="center-large">THE WILD LAND</head>
            <head type="main" rend="center-large">O PIONEERS!</head>
            <head type="main" rend="center">PART I</head>
            <head type="sub" rend="center">THE WILD LAND</head>
            <div2 type="chapter" n="1">
               <head type="main" rend="center">I</head>
               <pb n="3"/>
               <p>O<hi rend="smallcaps">NE</hi> January day, thirty years ago, the little town of
                  Hanover, anchored on a windy Nebraska tableland, was trying not to be blown away.
                  A mist of fine snowflakes was curling and eddying about the cluster of low drab
                  buildings huddled on the gray prairie, under a gray sky. The dwelling-houses were
                  set about haphazard on the tough prairie sod; some of them looked as if they had
                  been moved in overnight, and others as if they were straying off by themselves,
                  headed straight for the open plain. None of them had any appearance of permanence,
                  and the howling wind blew under them as well as over them. The main street was a
                  deeply rutted road, now frozen hard, which ran from the squat red railway station
                     <pb n="4"/> and the grain "elevator" at the north end of the town to the lumber
                  yard and the horse pond at the south end. On either side of this road straggled
                  two uneven rows of wooden buildings; the general merchandise stores, the two
                  banks, the drug store, the feed store, the saloon, the post-office. The board
                  sidewalks were gray with trampled snow, but at two o'clock in the afternoon the
                  shopkeepers, having come back from dinner, were keeping well behind their frosty
                  windows. The children were all in school, and there was nobody abroad in the
                  streets but a few rough-looking countrymen in coarse overcoats, with their long
                  caps pulled down to their noses. Some of them had brought their wives to town, and
                  now and then a red or a plaid shawl flashed out of one store into the shelter of
                  another. At the hitch-bars along the street a few heavy work-horses, harnessed to
                  farm wagons, shivered under their blankets. About the station everything was
                  quiet, for there would not be another train in until night.</p>

               <ab>On the sidewalk in front of one of the stores sat a little <persName
                  ref="#pers_emil_bergson">Swede boy</persName>, crying
                  bitterly. He was about five years old. His black cloth coat was much too big for
                  him and made him look like a little old man. His shrunken brown flannel dress had
                  been washed many times and left a long stretch of stocking between the hem of his
                  skirt and the tops of his clumsy, copper-toed shoes. His cap was pulled down over
                  his ears; his nose and his chubby cheeks were chapped and red with cold. He cried
                  quietly, and the few people who hurried by did not notice him. He was afraid to
                  stop any one, afraid to go into the store and ask for help, so he sat wringing his
                  long sleeves and looking up a telegraph pole beside him, whimpering, "My kitten,
                  oh, my kitten! Her will fweeze!" At the top of the pole crouched a shivering gray
                  kitten, mewing faintly and clinging desperately to the wood with her claws. The
                  boy had been left at the store while his sister went to the doctor's office, and
                  in her absence a dog had chased his kitten up the pole. The little creature had
                  never been so high before, and she was too frightened to move. Her master was sunk
                  in despair. He was a little country boy, and this village was to him a very
                  strange and perplexing place, where people wore fine clothes and had hard hearts.
                  He always felt shy and awkward here, and wanted to hide behind things for fear
                  some one might laugh at him. Just now, he was too unhappy to care who laughed. At
                  last he seemed to see a ray of hope: his sister was coming, and he got up and ran
                  toward her in his heavy shoes. His sister was a tall, strong girl, and she walked
                  rapidly and resolutely, as if she knew exactly where she was going and what she
                  was going to do next. She wore a man's long ulster (not as if it were an
                  affliction, but as if it were very comfortable and belonged to her; carried it
                  like a young soldier), and a round plush cap, tied down with a thick veil. She had
                  a serious, thoughtful face, and her clear, deep blue eyes were fixed intently on
                  the distance, without seeming to see anything, as if she were in trouble. She did
                  not notice the little boy until he pulled her by the coat. Then she stopped short
                  and stooped down to wipe his wet face. "Why, Emil! I told you to stay in the store
                  and not to come out. What is the matter with you?" "My kitten, sister, my kitten!
                  A man put her out, and a dog chased her up there." His forefinger, projecting from
                  the sleeve of his coat, pointed up to the wretched little creature on the pole.
                  Oh, Emil! Did n't I tell you she'd get us into trouble of some kind, if you
                  brought her? What made you tease me so? But there, I ought to have known better
                  myself." She went to the foot of the pole and held out her arms, crying, "Kitty,
                  kitty, kitty," but the kitten only mewed and faintly waved its tail. Alexandra
                  turned away decidedly. "No, she won't come down. Somebody will have to go up after
                  her. I saw the Linstrums' wagon in town. I'll go and see if I can find Carl. Maybe
                  he can do something. Only you must stop crying, or I won't go a step. Where's your
                  comforter? Did you leave it in the store? Never mind. Hold still, till I put this
                  on you." She unwound the brown veil from her head and tied it about his throat. A
                  shabby little traveling man, who was just then coming out of the store on his way
                  to the saloon, stopped and gazed stupidly at the shining mass of hair she bared
                  when she took off her veil; two thick braids, pinned about her head in the German
                  way, with a fringe of reddish-yellow curls blowing out from under her cap. He took
                  his cigar out of his mouth and held the wet end between the fingers of his woolen
                  glove. "My God, girl, what a head of hair!" he exclaimed, quite innocently and
                  foolishly. She stabbed him with a glance of Amazonian fierceness and drew in her
                  lower lip&#8212;most unnecessary severity. It gave the little clothing drummer
                  such a start that he actually let his cigar fall to the sidewalk and went off
                  weakly in the teeth of the wind to the saloon. His hand was still unsteady when he
                  took his glass from the bartender. His feeble flirtatious instincts had been
                  crushed before, but never so mercilessly. He felt cheap and ill-used, as if some
                  one had taken advantage of him. When a drummer had been knocking about in little
                  drab towns and crawling across the wintry country in dirty smoking-cars, was he to
                  be blamed if, when he chanced upon a fine human creature, he suddenly wished
                  himself more of a man? While the little drummer was drinking to recover his nerve,
                  Alexandra hurried to the drug store as the most likely place to find Carl
                  Linstrum. There he was, turning over a portfolio of chromo "studies" which the
                  druggist sold to the Hanover women who did china-painting. Alexandra explained her
                  predicament, and the boy followed her to the corner, where Emil still sat by the
                  pole. "I'll have to go up after her, Alexandra. I think at the depot they have
                  some spikes I can strap on my feet. Wait a minute." Carl thrust his hands into his
                  pockets, lowered his head, and darted up the street against the north wind. He was
                  a tall boy of fifteen, slight and narrow-chested. When he came back with the
                  spikes, Alexandra asked him what he had done with his overcoat. "I left it in the
                  drug store. I could n't climb in it, anyhow. Catch me if I fall, Emil," he called
                  back as he began his ascent. Alexandra watched him anxiously; the cold was bitter
                  enough on the ground. The kitten would not budge an inch. Carl had to go to the
                  very top of the pole, and then had some difficulty in tearing her from her hold.
                  When he reached the ground, he handed the cat to her tearful little master. "Now
                  go into the store with her, Emil, and get warm." He opened the door for the child.
                  "Wait a minute, Alexandra. Why can't I drive for you as far as our place? It's
                  getting colder every minute. Have you seen the doctor?" "Yes. He is coming over
                  to-morrow. But he says father can't get better; can't get well." The girl's lip
                  trembled. She looked fixedly up the bleak street as if she were gathering her
                  strength to face something, as if she were trying with all her might to grasp a
                  situation which, no matter how painful, must be met and dealt with somehow. The
                  wind flapped the skirts of her heavy coat about her. </ab>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
